<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvord of reproof to the priests or ministers, who boast of their ministery and ordinances, and yet live in pride, disdain, persecution, &amp;c. Shevving what such are; and how little cause they have to exclaim against those who separate from them. As also a word to the papists discovering their foundation to be carnal and sandie. In a letter sent to some supposed priests or Jesuites in the north, by William Tomlinson.</title>
            <author>Tomlinson, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94750</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E691_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206966</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866044</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866044</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118304</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94750)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118304)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 107:E691[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvord of reproof to the priests or ministers, who boast of their ministery and ordinances, and yet live in pride, disdain, persecution, &amp;c. Shevving what such are; and how little cause they have to exclaim against those who separate from them. As also a word to the papists discovering their foundation to be carnal and sandie. In a letter sent to some supposed priests or Jesuites in the north, by William Tomlinson.</title>
                  <author>Tomlinson, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Wayte, and are to be sold at the Pavement in York,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill: 13".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118304:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Word of Reproof TO THE PRIESTS OR MINISTERS, WHO Boaſt of their Miniſtery and Ordinances, and yet live in Pride, Diſdain, Perſecution, &amp;c. <hi>SHEVVING</hi> What ſuch are; and how little cauſe they have to exclaim againſt thoſe who ſeparate from them. AS ALSO A word to the Papiſts Diſcovering their Foundation to be carnal and ſandie. In a LETTER ſent to ſome ſuppoſed Prieſts or Jeſuits in the North, BY <hi>WILLIAM TOMLINSON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>In the Cup wherein ſhe hath filled to you, fill to her double.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Wayte,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Pavement in <hi>York,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:118304:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118304:2"/>
            <head>A word of Reproof to the Prieſts or Miniſters who boaſt of their Miniſtery and Ordinances and yet live in Pride, diſdain, perſecution, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Ye Prieſts,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">I do not call you Prieſts out of deriſion (I love not that) though ſome muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride you. But becauſe moſt of you were ordained to your office under that very name, and few or none of you have renounced that your Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation Secondly becauſe you conform yourſelves more to the Prieſts under the Law, then to the Miniſters of the Goſpel. The truth is ye are not worthy of that name: for it is a name peculiar to the Saints onely, and to all the Saints under the miniſtration of the Goſpel. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5, 9. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.6.</note> you call your ſelves the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Jeſus Chriſt, when as you do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing reſemble him. You have nothing to bear you out to be ſo, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly great ſwelling words. As the Jews once glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the Temple, when the Lord was departed out of it, crying, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord,</hi> as if thoſe great words had been argument enough to bear it out to be the Temple of the Lord, when he had left it. <hi>So you cry the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Lord, the Miniſters of Lord; the Miniſters of Chriſt, the Miniſters of Chriſt; the Miniſters of the Goſpel, the Miniſters of the Goſpel;</hi> as if thoſe great words were enough to prove you to be ſo; when as the Lord is departed from you and your
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118304:3"/>Miniſtery: and leaves it to become as the blood of a dead man, <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.3. In which no life is to be found but death, and ſtifeling of the Spirit. For that holy unction which moves upon the hearts of the <hi>Babes of Chriſt,</hi> and weaklings, in ſtead of being ſtrengthened, is among you ſtrangled, and rendred as deluſion, and fancie, and a thing which they muſt not truſt to, though this teſtimony be given of it from above, <hi>That it is Truth,</hi> and is no lie, and is the onely preſervative againſt ſeducing; and the guide or Teacher that keepes us abiding in Chriſt. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.26.27. For that Unction is Chriſt moving in us, and as he is according to that obeyed and yielded to, ſo he abides with us, and we abide in him. By that he leads on from truth to truth, and ſo from ſtrength to ſtrength, from comfort to comfort, from light to light, untill he lead into clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and fulneſs, and preſent us perfect before God and the Father, without ſpot and blemiſh before his Throne. Yet dare you blaſpheme this holy Spirit, which is no other but Chriſt himſelfe in fleſh, which you deny, fighting againſt him in every appearance of his in fleſh, and thereby manifeſtly declare your ſelves to be Antichriſt, and not the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, as you proudly boaſt your ſelves to be. He is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt that denies the Father and the Son, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.22. He that denies the Son, denies the Father alſo, for they two are one. And he that denies the Spirit or Unction that moves upon the hearts of Chriſts Schollars, and fights againſt it, when he would come and appear in fleſh, he denies both the Father and the Son, for theſe three are one. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.3. Every Spirit that confeſſes not Jeſus Chriſt come in fleſh is not of God: and this is that Spirit of Antichriſt whereof you have heard
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118304:3"/>that it ſhould come and even now already is it in the world. I ſay every Spirit that confeſſes not Chriſt come in the fleſh: for ſo the words are more truely rendred as ſome of you know. And ſo rendred they hold forth a conſtant Character or mark of that Spirit of Antichriſt. It doth not confeſs Chriſt come, (that is when he comes or appears) in fleſh, or in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. To ſay (as it is tranſlated in the Engliſh) every Spirit that confeſſes not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh; To ſay thus, is not a full Character of Antichriſt: For the Papiſts themſelves, and the Pope (whom you all ſay is Antichriſt,) He doth not deny but that Jeſus Chriſt is come, that is, once came in fleſh. Therefore in that ſence it diſcovers not Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. But both He and They, and You do all deny and fight againſt Chriſt come in fleſh of his ſervants, that is when he comes and appears in them. Therefore in the ſame ſence wherein it diſcovers him, (I mean the Pope,) to be Antichriſt, in the ſame it diſcovers you alſo to be Antichriſt For as he fights againſt the Appearances of the Lord and confeſſes not Chriſt in thoſe commings of his in fleſh, whereby he leads his people out of his myſtery: ſo no more do you confeſs Chriſt in thoſe commings of his in fleſh now, whereby he would lead his people out from under your myſtery. So that I ſay the Spirit of Antichriſt manifeſts it ſelf in you: and yet are you bold to cry up your ſelves, <hi>The Miniſters of Chriſt; The Miniſters of the Goſpel:</hi> as if you were able by theſe words to ſtrike dead all Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the contrary. You do wiſely in your generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to keep you there, and ſo to fear and dazle the minds of men with thoſe great words, keeping them off as far as you can from reaſoning about it: making
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118304:4"/>them by your great words of Goſpel Miniſters, and I know not what, to fear even to queſtion whether you be ſo or not. Oh ye Oppoſers, will you always ſtrive againſt the Truth? how many of you who ſtand in the publique Miniſtery (as you call it) have been leaders of the People out of Error? How many of you have lighted the People by your examples to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake and renounce the world and the things thereof; yea I may ſay, The Relliques of the Romiſh traſh, that Idol ſervice Book, and all the trumpery of it? Nay have not the People, therein rather taught you? are they firſt in the obedience? do not you ſtick to it untill the ſtream of the People ſhame you from it; and the fear of looſing of your livings (as you call them) make you to part with it? Is it not thus with you alſo in other appearances of Chriſt, when he comes in fleſh in weakneſs, in his ſervants to conſume the myſtery of iniquity? do you not ſtand out ſtriving and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing untill the laſt? If you can eſpie failings and weakneſſes in that weak fleſh in which Chriſt comes, thoſe you uſe as inſtruments to fight withall againſt his appearings in that weak fleſh: and ſo you ſtumble at that ſtumbling ſtone. Yea you ſpeak evil of that which God approves of. If one come to you in meekneſs and calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſpirit uſing gentleneſs and patience towards you, over-maſtering you with reaſonings out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Oh then you clamour, ſuch a one is a dangerous fellow; He is as ill as a eſuite; Its as dangerous to come in his company as to go into an houſe infected with the plague; ſuch like railing accuſations proceed from you to ſcar the people, and to turn them away from trying the Spirits whether they be of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to command, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1. On the other ſide, if
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118304:4"/>one come in the true ſeverity of the Spirit as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Steven</hi> and others, yea as Chriſt the Prince of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs himſelf ſometimes did, and tell you what you are, warning you of the judgements that ſhall come upon you, then ſuch are cryed out againſt as judging, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious railing perſons. Let the innocent nature of the Lamb come to you in what way he will, whether mourning, or piping and dancing, whether in Auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or more liberty, yet you will attribute it all to the Devill. Let us tell you that the Lord teaches us inwardly by his Spirit, you ſay that's the ſpirit of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion. Let us ſay nothing of that but onely bring the writings of the Scriptures, then you ſay the Devill can put Scripture into mens mouths. Tis true, the Devil can put Scripture into mens mouthes; but conſider into whoſe monthes he doth put Scripture, whether into the mouthes of thoſe who would deſtroy his works, or of thoſe who uphold them. Indeed where a Kingdom of Fride and vain glory and covetouſneſs, and pomp of the world and ſuch like works of the Devil is upheld by Scripture, there its likely that the Devill doth put Scripture into mens mouthes, teaching them to wreſt it to their own deſtruction. But its ſtrange that the Devill ſhould put Scripture into mens mouthes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy his works therewith: ſhall we ſay that Chriſt is become now an upholder of the works of darkneſs, and the Devill a deſtroyer of them? This is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of ſuch Doctrine when you ſay, Its the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill that puts Scripture into the mouthes of ſuch as would deſtroy his works. You call your ſelves, <hi>The Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> But if you be not ſo, and yet ſay you are, conſider in calmneſs of minde what you then are. Some called themſelves Jews and were
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118304:5"/>not, and this was Blaſphemy. So to ſay that you are Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, if you be not ſo, whats this but Blaſphemy? For do not you Blaſpheme that holy Name when you aſcribe to him ſuch Miniſters as love the world and the things of it, But hate his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren whom he hath choſen out of the world. Them whom he hath made as ſignes and wonders in the world by ſome appearances of his in them, them ye hate. Yea though words have faln ſometimes from your own mouthes, which have driven ſome of them from you, yet you hate and oppoſe them for obeying that which your own mouthes have uttered. When you have told the People that they worſhip God in vain if they have but the traditions of man for their ground, yet if any of them hereupon have left your traditions you have been their greateſt enemies. Thus you hate the practiſe of Chriſtianity, though you ſometimes ſpeak of it. You hate to deny your ſelves, and to take up your Croſs, and follow Chriſt. You hate to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to thoſe of low degree, and to make them your equalls, leſt your familiarily bring you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. You hate the way of Chriſts allowance for his Miniſters: namely, to receive onely whats freely given, and of them onely who receive ſpirituall things of you. You hate the way and manner of Chriſts Miniſtration: and chuſe rather the manner of the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of the Nations. <hi>Paul</hi> reaſoned with them in the Synagogues, he ſuffered others to ſpeak to him and reaſon with him in the Synagogues, This you hate. Chriſt and his true Miniſters Preached without Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before and after as you do, and this you hate. In the Churches, or aſſemblings of Beleevers they might all Prophecy, as they received the gift, and power,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118304:5"/>one by one, but this you hate. In theſe, and in many other things you hate to be reformed. Shewing forth to every one your diſlike of the things of Chriſt, and yet you bluſh not to boaſt your ſelves to be the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Jeſus Chriſt. Conſider if this be not to Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme his name: and again conſider it. Lay aſide Paſſion, and conſider alſo whether that ſpirit of <hi>Jeze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, Rev.</hi> 2.20. Do not rather act in you, who called her ſelf a Propheteſſe, and yet taught the ſervants of the Lord to commit fornication, and to eat things ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed unto Idols. Do not you keep the People in that ſpirituall fornication which all Nations have been drunk with, even to worſhip God after the traditions of men; and ſo to eat things ſacrificed to Idols: things dedicated to your Idols of Honour and covetouſneſs, and your bellies, I ſay things dedicated to theſe, and upheld for the honour of theſe; ſuch things, ſuch ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices muſt the People feed upon. But you ſhall not long continue to feed the flock with ſuch things; no nor your ſelves neither: for the Lord will deliver his flock from your mouth, that they may not be meat for you, as he hath promiſed. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.10.</p>
            <p>The Lord hath made me and others as examples among you for many years, and hath made our lives a ſpeaking voice to call out from your Miniſtry, and by his ſtrength hath held us as by an <hi>Anchor</hi> from return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to you; making us to abide in this our <hi>Teſtimony:</hi> And now I muſt alſo declare further againſt you (with the reſt of my fellow ſervants) then yet I have uttered, and diſcover to the People what you are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You are that Antichriſt</hi> (as I ſaid before) ſpoken of in the Scriptures <hi>Becauſe you deny Chriſt comming in fleſh.</hi> Some of you have been convinced of ſome things,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118304:6"/>and ſeemed to make out after them, untill the world ſtole upon your hearts, and then you have ſought to quench and ſmother thoſe motions both in your ſelves and others. Others of you have been at continuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance againſt the breakings forth of truth in every de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; and thus you ſtand in oppoſition againſt the truth. You neither enter in your felves, nor ſuffer thoſe who are entring to goe in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You are the falſe Prophets</hi> which are ſpoken of, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you come in ſheeps clothing, yet inwardly you are ravening <hi>Wolves,</hi> and now the day is breaking, and diſcovers you plainly to be ſo by your works. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 16. By their works yea ſhall know them ſaith our Lord, you are eaſie enough to be diſcerned, when men look upon your works. Indeed when men look upon your devotion, your prayers, your lifting up of your hands, and eyes to heaven, your ſighings, and faigned tone and expreſſions, your ſeeming affections and ſuch like, you hereby deceive the hearts of the ſimple. But theſe will not ſerve your turnes now, your Covering is too narrow, it will not hide your nakednes. You are brought to the touch ſtone. <hi>Your work, Your works,</hi> they are your diſcovery. Your workes are the works of <hi>Sodom,</hi> pride, idelnes, fulnes of bread, covetouſnes, wrath, malice, backbiting, perſecution, diſdainfulnes. Oh the proud diſdainfull ſpirit that is among you! Is it not juſt ſo with you as it was with the Phariſees? What doſt thou teach us ſaid they; and is not the ſame in your hearts alſo againſt all that ſay any thing againſt you, if they appear not to be brought up in your Schooles? But by ſuch as you ſo ſcornfully diſdain, even by ſuch ſhall you be overthrown and confounded.</p>
            <p>You have clamoured againſt others, calling them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118304:6"/>
               <hi>wandring Stars, and falling Stars;</hi> as if the region of your traditions and humain inventions had been the firmament of truth, and as if all that fell from theſe things, had falne from Heaven and from grace. But it will be made manifeſt to all men, that you are falne from the firmament of truth, from the wayes, and from the words of the Apoſtles, and are found wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring in the foggy miſts of humain inventions. You have had a whores forehead, impudent and bold to caſt thoſe names upon others, which do moſt properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to your ſelves. Whether are they the falling Stars who ariſe in their ſpirits caſting off every weight that bindes down to the earth, that they may walk up clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer to the example of their Lord Chriſt, and his holy Apoſtles: or they who fall downwards towards the earth, with <hi>Demas</hi> loving this preſent world; but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the footſteps of the Apoſtles; fixing their roots into the earth, being held faſt with the allurements thereof?</p>
            <p>You have called every one <hi>Deceivers,</hi> and <hi>Seducers,</hi> who have ſtepped forth from you, groping after the truth. But conſider well whether you your ſelves ſhall not be found <hi>Grand Seducers.</hi> Firſt conſider the <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Deceivers,</hi> how many they are whom this who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſpirit of fornication &amp; ſeducing doth poſſeſs. It ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth upon many waters, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1. And thoſe waters are Peoples, and Multitude, and Nations, and tongues. <hi>v.</hi> 15. And again its ſaid, all nations drink of the wine of the wrath of her fornication, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.3. And again, By thy ſorceries were all nations deceived. <hi>v.</hi> 23. Now at whoſe hands do all nations receive this cup of forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but at the hands of the nationall miniſteries? and who are the ſorcerers who deceive all nations but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118304:7"/>their nationall teachers? who in ſome things imitate the true meſſengers of the Lord, but thereby take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to oppoſe them the more ſtrongly in other things, and even in ſuch things, as wherein their remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out of <hi>Egipt,</hi> ſpirituall lyes: and ſo keep them as faſt lockt up in the houſe of Bondage as they can. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes</hi> to keep <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> after the fleſh ſtill in Pharaohs houſe of Bondage. A few that ſtart aſide out of theſe generall Deluſions cannot be they who thus deceive and ſeduce all nations. <hi>Again,</hi> look upon the ſpirit of Perſecution, the Bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſpirit, ſtained with blood: and where find we that? Who are the perſecuters; and who the perſecuted? Are not thoſe whom the nationall teachers call ſeducers the Perſecuted; and are not the nationall teachers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Perſecuters? Judge by this where to find the ſeducers, for this is none of the leaſt Characters. Its not the nature of the lamb to perſecute; nor of them that follow the lamb. No they come out of great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation. They are nailed to the Croſs of Chriſt; and for his ſake are ſlain all the day long: and are as ſheep appointed to the ſlaughter. But on the other ſide the Seducers and Deceivers drink blood. They thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and procure the blood of ſaints; not under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſaints, that was never known, but under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Deceivers, and Blaſphemers, and Hereticks, and ſuch like. And ſo in her is found Blood, Blood, Blood, even all the blood of any that are ſlain upon the earth; Blood of Prophets, Blood of Saints, Blood of the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of Jeſus. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.6. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.24. <hi>Again</hi> we may gueſſe at the Seducers, and Deceivers by the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pompe and Riches which they fall down to, and deck themſelves withall, for the whoriſh ſpirit which ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118304:7"/>is an earthly ſpirit, and ſo delighteth in an earthly kingdom; in the pretious things of the earth. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.4. They are every one for their gain from their quarter they can remove from worſe quarters to better for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more mony, at their pleaſure: and this is uſually their call from one place to another. There be few of them but one may hire them from one place to another for forty pounds more per annum, if there be but equall honor and other accommodations in both places, and thus are they the hirelings of men, bought and ſold for earthly riches, even as bruit beaſts in a market, and they that give moſt get them. Thus they preſs after the waies of Balaam, tempting the Lord untill he give them up to the ſwinge of their own hearts, as he did Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam. But it is otherwiſe with the true meſſengers of the Lord. They propheſie in ſackcloth, and the nearer that any one comes to the truth, the more he is made to die to this world, and to the things thereof.</p>
            <p>You call others <hi>Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> (which are termes that ſignify a ſeparation and diviſion from the truth, from the ſaints who ſtand in the truth, and from Chriſt.) You are full of names of Blaſphemy, and thats one character of the deluding ſpirit: your mouthes, I ſay, are full of ſuch names, but which of you ſhewes the people, how they come to be worthy of ſuch names, to whom you apply them; and why you call them ſo as you do. Its an eaſy thing to call any one by any name or odious terme falſly, and as you do, without ground for it. That we may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore underſtand better who they are, that are hereticks and ſchiſmaticks indeed let us mind where is the knot of all true union; the center in which all muſt meet, who do not ſeparate, and make ſchiſme. Is it not in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118304:8"/>Chriſt who is the Truth? Suppoſe that Chriſt were here in perſon upon earth, and a few deſpiſed men break off from the body of the Jews, (as once they did,) and follow him, all the reſt cleaving faſt ſtill to their Judaiſme: tell me now, whether are theſe few who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the body of the Jews, their rites and ceremonies to follow Chriſt, or they who ſtick ſtill in them, the Hereticks, and Schiſmaticks? So when Chriſts comes in Spirit, and calls a People out of Babylon, from the confuſion of mens inventions, which hath overſpread the Earth, and wherewith all nations are made drunk, a few in compariſon of the reſt, come out by degrees, the reſt ſtick ſtill in the Confuſion. Which of theſe now are the Seperatiſt, the Shiſmaticks, the Hereticks, in Scripture account, making a rent and Schiſme from Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are not they the further off from Schiſme and Hereſie, who obey Chriſt herein, and come out of Babylon, though they be but a few in compariſon of the reſt: for they follow him herein who is the knot of union: and ſo herein cannot be the Schiſmaticks and Hereticks and Separatiſts and Sectariſts which the Scripture condemnes. For their ſeparation from the confuſion, and them that dwell therein, is not a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from Chriſt, nor from truth, being ſtricktly commanded, and preſſed both by promiſe and threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tening. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. Come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues. And again 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. Wherefore come out from among them and be ye ſeparate ſaith the Lord, and touch not the unclean thing, and I will receive you; and will be a Father unto you, and ye ſhall be my ſons and daughters, ſaith the Lord Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. I ſay, comming out from your Humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118304:8"/>and from all other inventions of man, though never ſo finely guilded, is here commanded, being comprehended under the word Babylon. I know that you will put off from your ſelves the word Babylon, and apply it to Rome: and they at Rome will apply it to ſomething elſe: for it is not to be expected that the Merchants of Babylon ſhould confeſſe againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they are ſo; leſt people ſhould buy their Merchandize no more.</p>
            <p>Tell us what is Babylon outward if it be not a build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or frame of Humane inventions whoſe top pretends to reach to Heaven (as the Tower of Babel was intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do) and ſo promiſes to ſet People in thither. If it be any other thing tell us what it is.</p>
            <p>Now you either trade in theſe Humane inventions: or you trade with the pure Ordinances of Chriſt. If you trade with Humane inventions, and make ſale of them; then I think it will be found that you are in the number of the Merchants of Babylon, enriching your ſelves with the abundance of her delicacies, delicate carved images of your own brains, and of other mens: and if ſo it will be found no <hi>Hereſie, Schiſms,</hi> or unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable ſeparation to come out from amongſt you. If you ſay, that you trade with the pure Ordinances of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, (for traders you are) then I deſire to know which one of them you will avouch to be the pure Ordinance of Chriſt, anſwering the pattern as you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it.</p>
            <p>Secondly I deſire to know upon what ground you dare buy and ſell any pure Ordinance of Chriſt, or gift of the holy Ghoſt, (if it be ſo.)</p>
            <p>I know that you want not words to cry them up for the Ordinances of Chriſt. As the Jews did with the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118304:9"/>Temple; and as you do with your miniſtery; ſo you cry them up for the Ordinances of Chriſt, the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt, crying to the People, Oh take heed how you turn your backs on the Ordinances of Chriſt. But as I ſaid of your Miniſtery, ſo I ſay of your Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; It is not enough to ſay onely that they are ſo. Which of you take the pains to ſhew the People what the Ordinances of Chriſt were: and compares yours with them, that the People may ſee them to be ſo? The truth is you dare not bring them to the light, nor ſuffer them to come to the light, leſt they ſhould be made manifeſt. For they are as far different from the pure Ordinances of Chriſt, or practiſes of Chriſt, and his followers, as <hi>Nadabs</hi> and <hi>Abihu's</hi> ſtrange fire was from the true fire, if not further.</p>
            <p>You ſay, you have Baptiſme, you have prayer, you have Preaching, you have ſinging of Pſalms, and ſome of you have the Communion, and were not theſe Ordinances of Chriſt? I anſwer you <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> had their Cenſer, they had fire, and they had Incenſe; which things were commanded by the Lord. Yet for all this they did that which the Lord commanded them not. <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.1. And ſo you may have theſe things, and yet be as far off from the right as they were.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt compare your Baptiſme</hi> with that which the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of Chriſt practiſed. You Baptize Infants: where did they Baptize any? have you any example, or any rule for the Baptizing of them? Is not this built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſandy conjectures and conſequences of your own imaginations? I know that ſome of the acuteſt of you ſay, That it is built upon the Promiſe, which belongs to the children with their Fathers. But let ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118304:9"/>whether it was the Promiſe belonging to them; or their receiving of that Promiſe, that was the ground of Baptiſme. Which of the Apoſtles did adminiſter Baptiſme to any of thoſe to whom the Promiſe did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, untill they received that Promiſe by faith?</p>
            <p>As for your Prayer which you uſe before and after your Sermons, I know not one example left you for it, either by Chriſt, or by any of his Apoſtles. What can you plead for it, ſeeing they did not ſo? Did they fall ſhort in what they ought to do? what! was Chriſt and the Apoſtles unfaithfull in the work of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, to leave ſuch a thing out; and to leave it unto you to amend what they failed in? No, no, your praying before and after is for the honor and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence of your Idol which is to accompany it: and that is your Preaching: (be patient with this expreſſion untill you have the explication of it, for I ſhall not onely call it ſo, and there leave it, as you do with many things.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſay your Preaching is an Idol.</hi> I do not ſay that Preaching is an Idol. Preaching is publiſhing, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring abroad, or telling to one another openly, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by conference or any other way. Thus they preached or publiſhed, or told abroad what Chriſt had done to one that was deafe, and had an impediment in his ſpeech <hi>Mark</hi> 7.36. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they preached it, which word you know is uſed where preaching is expreſſed, and yet it ſignifies no more here but telling abroad; or publiſhing as it is rendered in the Engliſh. So likewiſe the multitude of Beleevers who were ſcattered abroad, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.1. Went every where Preaching the word. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. that is declaring it, or telling it abroad where ever they came: and this was Preaching, and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118304:10"/>to converſion too. So <hi>Pauls</hi> Preacling in the Synagogues, was it not for the moſt part <hi>Reaſoning with them. Acts</hi> 17.2.3. that is, ſpeaking to them, and ſuffering them to ſpeak to him. But you do Idolize the manner of the Heathen Oratorie made in Pulpits; and all other ſpeaking muſt give place to that, and fall down ſilent before that Idol: or elſe you will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Lawes upon them, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any manner of ſpeaking will not be ſilent, and fall down and worſhip that comely honourable manner of Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory when it ſhall be ſet up, then to Priſon with him, make him faſt.</hi> What's this but to do as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> did, when he had ſet up a golden image, and caſt thoſe that would not worſhip it into a fiery furnace? Did ever Truth ſtand in need of Priſons to make men fall down to it? Did ever any thing in that kinde, need priſon or furnace to make another thing ſtoop to it, except onely Idols? Did ever Chriſt or any of his Apoſtles call to Magiſtrates, and Conſtables, and other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers to take others away to priſon who interrupted them? or needed they any other thing to keep men ſilent while they ſpake, beſides the Authority and Power of their words? Surely if you be their ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors as you would have men beleeve, and if your Preaching be like theirs, you would not need any other thing to make men ſilent but the power of your words. But its an Idol, and ſo needeth iron to uphold and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it: and to faſten it as it were in a wall leſt it fall. It may be ſome will ſay, Hath not God converted ſouls by this manner of Preaching in Pulpits? I anſwer if any were thereby converted, it was by ſome words of Truth falling upon the hearts of the hearers, which might have had the ſame effect in other manner of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118304:10"/>ſpeaking: and therefore the converſon of ſuch is not to be aſcribed to that Idolized manner of Preaching Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Pulpits: but to the Power of Truth which ought to have liberty to be ſpoken in other manner, but cannot for that Idol. I do willingly give my Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that the times of ignorance God winked at, and was pleaſed to ſtep in, and give much power ſometimes to the words of ſome who have ſpoken in that way, eſpecially to ſuch as have been under ſome ſuffering for not being fully conformable. Yea Babylon it ſelf can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not keep him out, but for his choſen ſake he will ſpeak to them there, even in the midſt of confuſion. But what then! now when light is breaking out, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering things more clearly, He cals upon all men to repent, and forſake the Error of their doings: and he that doth not follow the light, ſhall have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left him to uphold, but an Idol. For God is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting out of that which is not his own purely: and will leave it dead and dry, without life, without nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Yea he hath already withdrawn himſelf, and where formerly ſome life hath been found, now it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as the blood of a dead man. <hi>Again,</hi> if your manner of Preaching be not an Image, an Idol of your own, or other mens imaginations; but the pure off-ſpring of the Spirit: then tell us how it comes to paſs, that you can limit that holy Spirit now by the hour: doth the Spirit Order you, and adminiſter words and matter to you by the hour; or you Order him and keep him to your hour? O vain men, is it not the Idol of your own heads; the formings of your own brain; your woven and carved Oration-like ſpeeches, that you have this power over; to reach to what length you would have them, and to ſtop where
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118304:11"/>you would have them? They who have taſted of the Spirits miniſtring by them can witneſs that they then could not be ſtretched out to the hour, or limitted by the hour. <hi>Again,</hi> is not your Preaching an Idol; when as you uphold it onely for <hi>Gain?</hi> Its from your own mouthes; Take away livings, ſay you, (that is tithes and other hire) and what will become of the Goſpel? that is of your Goſpel. Oh ye earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirited men, doth the care of the Goſpel lie onely upon the ſhoulders of Hirelings? Surely ſurely, the time was when as the truth of the Goſpel was upheld by ſuffering the loſs of all things: and is it now upheld by hire? It was upheld, and alſo ſpread abroad by a few ſufferers; but now it ſeems its otherwiſe. No hire, no Goſpel: no Livings, no Preaching. I think ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. Such is your care of the Goſpel. You are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be called Goſpel Preachers, and Goſpel Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: and yet the want of hire will divide between you and your Goſpel. Take away the one, and take away the other alſo: for ſo you ſpeak, plain out, and are not aſhamed. Wo is us, hath God committed his Goſpel to ſuch careleſs ones? hath he hung it upon ſo tickle a point, and in theſe times when men are ready every where to withdraw their ſtipends, but onely that they are held to it by awe. No, no, your Goſpel, and your Preaching is your <hi>Diana,</hi> an Idol, a gainful Idol; and by that craft you have your gain. If you ſhould let the magnificence of it fall to the ground your gain were loſt. And therefore it behoves you to cry it up, as the Epheſians did their <hi>Diana. Act.</hi> 19.24, 25, 26, 27, 28. Cry it up with a ſhout and noiſe of words, with ſtaves and clubs, and Conſtables and Bayliffes, and ſines and Priſons, for this will be your beſt Argument.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118304:11"/>Tell the People ingeniouſly as <hi>Demetrius</hi> did, That by this craft or Art you have your wealth, and therefore it behoves you to uphold it: Not that you care for the Goſpel any further then its made a gainful trade; and upheld by you as an Idol, to bring in your gain: for take away gain, and farewell your Goſpel and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: all dies with hire if that be taken away. Much more may be ſaid to your Preaching, but I paſs on to your ſinging.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You have Pſalms indeed,</hi> but how come you by them? In the Primitive Church, that is, in the firſt gathering of Saints out of the world into fellowſhips one with another by the Apoſtles, they had <hi>Pſalms,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26 One had a Pſalm, another a Revelation, another an interpretation. They had all theſe and ſuch like gifts given them by the Spirit, which miniſtered to every one ſeverally as he pleaſed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. But whence have you your Pſalms? Doth the Spirit of the Lord miniſter them to you? Or do not you (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you want that gift) ſet up a Clark: or reader in many of your Congregations to ſupply the want of that gift; as if he were the miniſtring ſpirit to miniſter a Pſalm to all the Congregation: what is this pure fire from the Altar: or ſtrange fire like <hi>Nadabs,</hi> and <hi>Abihu's,</hi> taken from the Kitchin of your ſmoakie imaginations? Or elſe you have your Pſalms from your Books, and ſo all times are alike to you; you can ſing when you will, and forbear when you will: which would not be if the ſpirit (which breathes when and where he liſteth) did adminiſter them to you: for he would rule you, and not you him. Did not Chriſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend on high, and give gifts to men for the work of his miniſtery? But you deſcend to make uſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118304:12"/>Rimes and Metters of men to make up with your miniſtery. I know and witneſs, that ſincerity of heart expreſſing and breathing forth it ſelf in theſe things in the time of ignorance, hath been accepted, and cheriſhed by the Lord: but now when light is come to diſcover them to be of humane invention, in reſpect of the form and uſe of them, and yet men cry them up for the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt: the Spirit of the Lord ariſes up in indignation againſt them, as they are ſo abuſed. If you ſay, where are thoſe gifts of ſinging which are ſpoken off<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there's no ſuch thing to be found. I Anſwer you. They are not to be found with you: you are the Land of Captivity, you are Babylon, we may ſit down by the Rivers of Babylon, weeping in remembrance of <hi>Zion</hi> (while we are held captive by you) for how ſhould any ſing the Lords ſongs in a ſtrange Land? The ſhadowes are not yet fled away: the winter is not yet over and gone: and therefore we cannot ſay to you, that the time of ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is come: we cannot tell you that the voice of the Turtle is to be heard in your Land. It may be it is heard ſomewhere, though you hear it not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly</hi> you have that among ſome of you which you call <hi>Communion.</hi> But where that Communion lies I cannot tell. If it were Communion with God and Chriſt, then the Nature of God and Chriſt, which they have communion with at that <hi>Supper</hi> (as you call it, though it be a dinner) would put forth it ſelf in the partakers of it. They would walk as children of light, and not as children of darkneſs, in the works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. If any man ſay, he hath fellowſhip (or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion) with God and walk in darkneſs, he lies, and doth not the Truth. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.6. But your Communion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118304:12"/>ſhewes forth no ſuch thing accompanying it. For men come to it proud; and they go away proud. They come covetous, and they go away covetous. They come perſecutors, and they go away perſecutors. They come worldly minded ones, and they go away world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly minded. Now they who are ſuch, know neither the the Father nor the Son nor have Communion or fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with them. Yea it may be they come Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, Oppreſſors, hard hearted task maſters of Egypt, liars, cheaters, Over-reachers defrauders, drunkards, ſwearers, whore-mongers, full of malice and revenge; and ſuch like. Thus they come, and thus they go as they came, having no participation or Communion of the Divine nature in their Spirits to alter them. But thus come and go in their ſinfull nature having Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the ſpirit of darkneſs, and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs while they pretend Communion with God: and thus go on eating and drinking unworthily they know not what: and you ſuffer them to do ſo, and do it with them: eating and drinking judgement to your ſelves, while you thus take the Name of God and Chriſt in vain. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. This is not to eat the Lords Supper This is not to eat the fleſh of Chriſt, and drink his blood: for then would ye become dead to this world with him, and Chriſt would live again in you. Take notice of the words which <hi>Paul</hi> the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the Lord ſpake. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. <hi>The Cup of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing which we bleſs,</hi> is it not the Communion of the blood of Chriſt? The bread which we break is it not the Communion of the Body of Chriſt? Now the right Communicants, are one bread, and one Body, being all made partakers of that one bread. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. which bread is Chriſt. But ye cannot be partakers of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118304:13"/>this bread, nor have Communion with it, ſo long as you are in your Gentiliſme or heatheniſh Nature, living in Pride, Covetouſneſs, Perſecution, oppreſſing, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaching, uncleanneſs, lies and ſuch like. For ſaith <hi>Paul, v.</hi> 21. Ye cannot drink the cup of the Lord, and the cup of Devils: ye cannot be partakers of the Lords Table, and of the table of devils. Now the things which the Gentiles ſacrifice, they ſacrifice to Devils, and not to God, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. Gentiles are every one in their Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliſing nature; and what ever they ſacrifice, that is, what ever worſhip they offer in pretence as to God, it is to Devils, and not to God. Though they ſay it is to God as the <hi>Athenians</hi> did <hi>Act.</hi> 17.23. Yet God ownes it not: ſuch as worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth, thoſe are they whom he ſeekes to worſhip him. As for thoſe who walk in the works of darkneſs, he hath not Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them, nor they with him. For what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion hath light with darkneſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have not ſo much as Communion one with another, in that which you call Communion: for which of you imparts to the reſt of the Communicants, as every one hath need. You are ſo far from Community in theſe outward things, that you will go to Law for your propriety one with another, if you apprehend your ſelves but a little wronged therein, contrary to the minde and counſell of Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.40.</p>
            <p>Thus it is apparent, for all your boaſting of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt, I ſay it is apparent, that you have but a counterfeit image of the form of ſome of them: and not the very true image of thoſe which you have. If you had the very expreſſe image of all the outward forms of Ordinances of Chriſt, or practiſes of the Apoſtles and Beleevers: yet theſe were poor things to boaſt of, and to be exalted with <hi>Laodicean</hi>-like for if
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118304:13"/>you had all theſe in form nearer then they are among any people in this Nation, yet if your ſpirits fall down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and become earthly, the Lord would leave them, and ſlip away from you to another people who ariſe in their ſpirits caſting off every weight, and the ſins which beſet them, or hinder them, that they might run with patience the race ſet before them. Yea let me tell you that if you had not onely a true image and form of Ordinances; but alſo a form of godlineſs in words and ſayings of Chriſt and the Apoſtles alwayes in your mouthes; Yet all this could not binde or hold the Lord with you. But ſtill he would ſlip away from under all theſe; leaving theſe as huskes and chaffe for you who are diſobedient and earthly to feed upon, and boaſt your ſelves in; while in the mean time another people ſhould enjoy his preſence: for it is not any form of godlineſs that the Lord takes pleaſure in: but the Power, the Truth, the life, the ſpirit. And therefore he doth not binde us his ſervants to abide in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with any, that live in any form of godlineſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Power. But commands us by his Apoſtle to turn away from ſuch. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. And this is no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable Schiſme or ſeparation. So that whether we look at the form of Ordinances, or at the Power of godlineſs we have warrant enough to turn away from you, and to have no fellowſhip in your holy things. For as I ſaid, you have but an image of ſome Ordinances onely, and that without the life and Power of them. <hi>Others traditions of</hi> Chriſt you do altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſown, for they will not ſtand with your profit, as namely to deny your ſelves to take up his Croſſe daily and follow Chriſt: which is a great Ordinance of Chriſt; for without this one cannot be his Diſciple.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118304:14"/>Again you diſown the liberty which Chriſt hath given to all his members, namely. Ye may all prophecie, one by one, that all may learn, and all may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted. You diſown every gift that would bring to nought the magnificence of your <hi>Diana.</hi> But what you can form to profit your ſelves withall that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: And can adde alſo other things, (to make Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of them) which have no ſhadow of any footſtep in the practiſes of the true Meſſengers of Chriſt, as namely, Your Marrying of Perſons for mony; your buryings for mony; and your moſt abſurd Mortuaries or ſtipend which you challenge for the dead. Your funeral ſermons for mony alſo. I am weary with raking in theſe filthy puddles: which are fit for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſwine to wallow in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And thus</hi> though you both <hi>adde and diminiſh</hi> from the things of Chriſt, and <hi>Counterfeit</hi> other things which you uphold for your gain; yet all that ſeparate from you muſt be cried againſt as <hi>Hereticks Sectariſts, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, Separatiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed there is a ſeparation, which I do not here plead for: and thats a ſeparation upon conceit of ones own holineſs, becauſe they are devout in ſome outward obſervations of worſhip more then other men: ſuch as are ſpoken of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.5. Stand by thy ſelf, come not near to me, for I am holier then thou. Theſe are a ſmoke in my noſe, a fire that burneth all the day: and theſe were devout in holding up Ordinances: rather then they would have no ſacrifice they would ſacrifice in Gardens: and rather then they would have no incenſe they would offer it upon Altars of Brick <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. They are charged to be a people who walk after their own thoughts, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. Such alſo were the Phariſees, who
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118304:14"/>ſtood glorying in their own outſide painted holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and thanked God that they were not as other men, and even as this Publicane: when as within, they were full of rottenneſs, and all uncleanneſs: full of envy, wrath, malice, perſecution, diſdain, covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, pride and ſuch like. And all theſe they retained under a ſhew of godlineſs, and outward obſervation of Ceremonies and traditions of their Fathers. They were ſtrict in waſhing off the defilement which they had any way contracted, if water would have done it. They bare great reverence to the ſacrifices upon the Altar, which were Ordinances then in force. They made conſcience of paying tithe of all they had, even of Mint and Anniſe and Cummin. They were not wanting in prayers, and faſtings to the Lord, and their prayers were no ſhort ones, which gave all to think, that they were not weary of ſerving the Lord. Yea they compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sea and Land too to beget people to the Lord, to make proſelites: thus they appeared righteous unto men. But yet for all that they were but <hi>whited Sepulchres</hi> full of Hypocriſie, and iniquity, when that light came which was able to diſcover them: and to uncover their hearts by their works. Even by their covetouſneſs, and hard heartedneſs to the poor Widowes, by their love of honor, by their neglect of the weightier matters of the Law, Judgement, Mercy, Faith: as alſo by that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting ſpirit which was in them; and ſuch like: and yet theſe men added one thing more to gloſſe all the reſt over the better, they abhorred to be companions to Publicanes and ſinners, and blamed Chriſt for eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drinking with ſuch. Yea they made it matter of thankfulneſs to God, acknowledging it to be his work, that they were not ſuch: and thus they ſaid in their hearts, Stand by thy ſelf, for I am holier then
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118304:15"/>thou. There were ſome alſo ſpoken of in the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude,</hi> ungodly men, walking after their own luſts, ſenſuall, not having the Spirit <hi>ver.</hi> 19. Theſe ſeparated themſelves from the fellowſhip of thoſe Saints, who ſtood in the pure truth: turning the grace of God into laſciviouſneſs; the pure Love into wantonneſs. They crept in unawares, and drew an image of the pure Love and grace of God ſhed abroad upon the Saints, and in their carnall hearts it became wantonneſs, and laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: and ſo they withdrew themſelves again, and ſeparated from that holy fellow-ſhip to follow their ungodly luſts of uncleanneſs, covetouſneſs, gluttony and ſuch like. Now I ſay ſuch ſeparations as theſe I do not plead for. But I own and defend that ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the inventions and traditions and Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of men which is commanded in Scripture under the name Babylon. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.8. <hi>Ch.</hi> 51.6, 45. The whole chapters ſpeak much thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh ye Prieſts, ye Merchants of Babylon, out of the North there ariſed up a Nation against you, which ſhall make your Land deſolate.</hi> Ch. 50.3. ch. 51.48. <hi>It is time to ſeparate from your Babyloniſh inventions: for the hewers are already entered into your forreſt. Oh thou that dwelleſt upon many waters, thine end is come and the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of thy covetouſneſs</hi> Jer. 51.13. <hi>Thy ſtrength faileth,</hi> the mighty men of Babylon have forborn to fight: they have remained in their holds; they are become as women, Jer. 51.30. If my application fail, it will not fail long. <hi>Babylon the great is fallen, is fallen, and is becom the habitation of Devils, and the hold of every foul ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and a Cage of every unclean and hatefull bird. All Nations have drunk of the wine of the wrath of her forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations: and the Kings of the earth have committed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118304:15"/>with her; and the Merchants of the earth are wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed rich through the abundance of her delicacies,</hi> Rev. 18.2, 3. And for this cauſe is ſhe fallen, <hi>Becauſe ſhe made all nations drink of the wine of the wrath of her fornication.</hi> Rev. 14.8. Therefore to obey that voice from Heaven which hath ſaid in the hearts of many <hi>come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, &amp; that ye receive not of her plague;</hi> I ſay to obey this voice is not <hi>Hereſie, Schiſme,</hi> and ſuch a ſeparation as you have made it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hereſie and Schiſme and Separation and Sects</hi> rightly taken is this, To ſeparate, divide or make a rent and breach from the truth, and from them that dwell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: as namely from the Spirit and life of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and from ſuch Apoſtles and ſervants of his as have walked or do walk in that ſpirit, and in that life: and from them in that thing wherein there is truth. But you cannot be ſaid to be ſuch: you are far enough from the pathes and ſpirit too that dwelt in them. And therefore I leave it to the daylight which ſhall ariſe in mens conſciences to diſcover whether you your ſelves be not <hi>Grand Hereticks, grand Schiſmaticks, grand Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratiſts,</hi> ſwarving from the Life and Spirit of them, whom you cry up in words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſuch grand Schiſmaticks</hi> and <hi>Hereticks</hi> you are, that you would ſtop up the way for ever (if it were in your power) to keep men from returning back again into the purity and Simplicity of that truth from which you are ſeparated: crying out to the people, to take heed of Hereſie and Schiſme, and ſeparation, ſcaring them with theſe termes, when as you your ſelves are the Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks and Separatiſts from the Truth: and ſo while you bid others beware of it, you hold them faſt in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O ye Deceivers</hi> God will require his flock at your hands. Their Redeemer is ſtrong, the Lord of Hoſtes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118304:16"/>is his Name, he ſhall throughly plead their cauſe, and deliver them out of your hands. <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.33, 34. <hi>Eze.</hi> 34.10, 11.12, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I paſs on now to other termes which you have uſed againſt ſuch as have preſſed towards the Truth. For I muſt fill to you in your own Cup. You call others <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and unſtable</hi> from the words of <hi>Peter</hi> in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Epiſtle. <hi>Ch.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 16. And ſay that they wreſt the Scriptures to their own deſtruction. We will firſt conſider theſe words as they are tranſlated: and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards as they may be more truely tranſlated: and ſee to whom they may moſt properly be applied. <hi>Firſt</hi> for the word <hi>unlearned:</hi> we ſhall ſee who they are that are unlearned, by taking notice what Learning is. <hi>Learning is nothing</hi> elſe but <hi>A right underſtanding of things as they are in themſelves:</hi> an appendance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is <hi>Eloquence,</hi> which is a clear uttering of things rightly underſtood, to the underſtandings of others. I have ſeldom heard of any learned man of any depth of Judgement that will ſay that Eloquence lies in dark ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and hidden words, and vainglorious ſounds of words which ſome delight in: but in a plain, perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, clear expreſſion that comes home to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings of others: thats to ſpeak the thing out, thats Eloquence. I know well, that there is an Eloquence, which is Eloquence but onely to ſome, to others it is an unknown tongue, I am not againſt this, if it do clearly and pertinently expreſſe Truth: let men ſpeak out truth as they can: but yet minde what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, I had rather ſpeak five words with the underſtanding, then ten thouſand words in an unknown tongue: ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing home to others underſtanding comes neareſt to the end of ſpeaking. Now here is the very End of Schooles
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118304:16"/>and Univerſities, namely, To bring men to a right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of things as they are in themſelves, in truth, and to profit their utterance and demonſtration of that truth that is in things, and for this end are diſputations in Schooles about Queſtions Morall, Philoſophicall, Divine, &amp;c. Now he that reaches neareſt home to theſe Ends, namely to underſtand things as they are really in themſelves, and to utter forth the ſame to the underſtandings of others, he is the moſt Learned, Let his Education be what it will: for he reaches that, which all Univerſities are erected for in the right ends of them. Further the top of all learning, or the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal learning lies in a clear underſtanding of the higheſt things, or of the things of Chriſt and the clear Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of theſe things to the underſtandings of others by words which the ſpirit adminiſters; is the <hi>chiefeſt Eloquence.</hi> If learning and Eloquence conſiſt in any thing elſe let them who liſt, declare wherein it lies. Now theſe things being well weighed, may in ſome meaſure diſcover to us who are learned, who are unlearned. Namely thoſe who beſt reach theſe ends, be it in what way ſoever, by ſtudie, by Education, or by Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they are the moſt learned. If one man be brought up at an Univerſity, and ſpend many years there: ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther followes his employment in ſome outward calling, walking in obedience to the light thats in him. Now let theſe two meet at the end of ſeven years; and he that hath followed his calling, and the light communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to him be better inſtructed in the myſteries of Jeſus Chriſt, then the other; and be more able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare them with profit to the hearers then the other: yea to confound the other by the Scriptures, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his ignorance and diſobedience: then let any ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118304:17"/>man tell us which of theſe two men is the more Learned, and which is the more unlearned in the things of Chriſt. Now whether there be not many preſidents of theſe afforded in this Nation of ours, let the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of theſe times teſtifie. And yet the unlearned ignorant Prieſts cry out againſt others as unlearned, who have more learning then themſelves. <hi>Now for the word unſtable</hi> that which is ſtability they account Inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility. For ſtability is to ſtick cloſe to the Lord, and to follow him whitherſoever he goes, it is not to fix our roots into the earth, and there to ſtick faſt. Suppoſe that when the Lord led his people out of Egypt, ſome would ſit down by the fleſhpots of Egypt, others would ſet forward, but yet ſit down by the way, at ſome of thoſe places where the cloud that led them ſtood ſtill, others where the tabernacle was pitched for a ſeaſon, others would turn back again unto Egypt: but others as <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> followed the Lord fully: removing from place to place, not turning back again in their hearts, but keeping intirely to the guide that led them. Now tell me, were <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> the unſtable ones, who could no where ſit down with the reſt that turned back in their hearts to Egypt: or they who had moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for a time to go forward, but afterwards turned back again? <hi>So the Lamb</hi> may have as many removes out of Babylon and Egypt ſpirituall for ought I know; and if ſo: then whether are they who follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goes; or they who have motions forth of this Babylon, but turn back again in their hearts, chuſing rather to ſit down at eaſe there, then to go on. I ſay which of theſe are the unſtable ones? judge in your ſelves. But ſhall I tell you that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtability of many ſhall be laid to the charge of you
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118304:17"/>Prieſts. You have met them and buffetted them with your terrible words, and have turned away many a ſoul from following the Lamb. Yea I my ſelf have not been without buffettings from ſome of you. Others (whom my ſoul tenderly lookes upon with much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion) have broken from you, and have broken the Ice as it were, preſſing forward after the Truth, and to finde out the way for us towards Zion. Yet thorow the violence of your Tempeſts, have been made to turn into creekes for harbour, where to make their ſtand, leſt they ſhould be overwhelmed in your Tempeſts: and ſo have been ſlacked and taken off from their ſtabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in following the Lamb: and yet with an impudent for chead you brand that with inſtabilitie which is ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie and ſtrength. Let us now conſider of the words in a better tranſlation. The words of <hi>Peter</hi> in the Greek tongue are theſe: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. And they are tranſlated thus; Which they that are unlearned and unſtable wreſt. (I deſire tender ſpirits not to be offended, that I uſe words here which they underſtand not; for I ſpeak to thoſe that do underſtand the litterall ſenſe of them; and muſt deal with them a little with their own weapons.) The words which may more eaſily be underſtood if they were tranſlated nearer to the Greek words thus; <hi>Which they that are undiſcipled, and unfixed wreſt:</hi> for by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned is meant undiſcipled here in this place; and by unſtable is meant ſuch as are unfixed in their hearts to Jeſus Chriſt, and to his Croſſe. Now a man cannot be a Diſciple of Chriſt except he deny himſelf, and take up his Croſſe daily and follow Chriſt. So that the meaning is this plainly: which they who are undiſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled not taking up their Croſſe to follow Chriſt: who
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118304:18"/>are unfixed to Chriſt in their hearts halting between him and the world, do wreſt. For ſuch as theſe are the wreſters of the Scriptures to their own deſtruction. Theſe, becauſe there is an edge of Scripture againſt them, therefore they turn aſide the edge of it with their ſlippery and miſty interpretations, that ſo they may ſit at their eaſe enjoying the pleaſures of this world, and avoiding the Croſſe, rather then put their necks under the yoke of Chriſt. That theſe are the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned ones ſpoken off in this place is plain by the very word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies one undiſcipled: for when men unlearned in another ſenſe are ſpoken of, the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is uſed, which ſignifies illiterate: and in that ſence indeed <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were unlearned, that is they were illiterate or ungrammerd men, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.13. Now herein is the foul Error of the Prieſts who have altogether applied that in <hi>Peter</hi> to illiterate men, ſuch as <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf was who ſpoke them: whereas the words there are onely proper to undiſcipled men, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned in the Truths of Chriſt, diſobedient to him in their hearts. Theſe are the wreſters of Scripture to their own deſtruction. I apeal to your ſelvs, whether the very words do not fairly lead to this interpretation: or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hold out this very ſenſe without any further inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation. And ſo <hi>Peters</hi> unlearned ones that wreſt the Scriptures, are very applicable to the greateſt Doctors in the world. The moſt learned Rabbies, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators, and Diſputants in the world may be, and for the moſt part are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is undiſcipled: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubdued to the yoke of Chriſt; and ſo moſt fit to wreſt the Scriptures to their own deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Again let us leave the bare words and conſider of the dealings of the Lord with men, and from thence
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118304:18"/>take notice who are moſt likely to wreſt the Scriptures. How come we to underſtand the Truth? is it not a thing given? Now to whom is it given? Onely to learned men brought up at Univerſities? noe: the Lord chuſes few of thoſe to entruſt with the Knowledg of his Truth. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26, 27, 28. verſes. <hi>Not many wiſe,</hi> and ſo on. <hi>But God hath choſen the fooliſh things, and weak things: and baſe things, and deſpiſed things, to do his works by: that no fleſh ſhould glory,</hi> verſ. 29. Now if he will chuſe ſuch for his works, who dare contradict; or ſay unto him why doſt thou ſo? or clamor againſt his inſtruments, calling them unleamed, except onely ſuch as dare ſay any thing? Did not Chriſt thank his Father for hiding the myſteries of his Kingdom from the wiſe and prudent, and revealing them to babes? <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. And yet you would arrogate to your ſelves a priviledge of right underſtanding the Truth by vertue of your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired wiſdom, by humane learning, and vilifie all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that want that learning, as wreſters of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to their own deſtruction: when as often times that which you call wreſted, is the very Truth lying in plain words in the letter. The true Knowledge of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, is not given to Humane Learning, but to obedience to the will of God. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.17. If any man will do his will, he ſhall know of the Doctrine, whither it be of God. Its plain therefore, that the moſt ſelf-denying perſons are moſt likely to know the Doctrine of Chriſt beſt; to them its promiſed. Every degree of ſelf deniall done in obedience to God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves a vail from off the Creatures underſtanding, and ſo he going on therein, hath an abundant entrance opened unto him into the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord: and the want of Humane learning cannot rob
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118304:19"/>the Obedient of this Entrance into the Kingdom of light: whereas on the contrary Diſobedience (though accompanied with never ſo much humane learning and wiſdom) folds up a man under blindneſs, and ſtrong deluſions; even to beleeve lies. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11. And yet by you all truth muſt be aſcribed to Univerſities, and Humane learning, though God regard them not: and nothing taken notice of from ſuch as want that Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane learning, though God make uſe of ſuch for the moſt part, as his fitteſt inſtruments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> you have not been ſparing in calling others <hi>Blaſphemers,</hi> but what Blaſphemy is one ſhall ſeldom hear from you. To Blaſpheme is to ſpeak evil of one falſely, to ſlander, to reproach, to revile, to ſtrike thorow ones name with reproaches. Thus to revile the actings of the holy Spirit, is to Blaſpheme the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit: as ſome of the Phariſees did revile the words and actions of Chriſt, when that Spirit put forth it ſelf eminently in him in mighty works: they ſaid ſpitefully and revilingly, that he did it by Beelzebub the Prince of the Devils. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf while he was <hi>Saul,</hi> a Perſecuter, was alſo guilty in part of Blaſphemy againſt that holy name, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil thereof: and he looked upon it as a great thing that he obtained mercy. He did it ignorantly in unbelief. Thus alſo <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf and others were Blaſphemed afterwards. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. As we be ſlander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly reported, &amp;c. now the word ſlanderouſly report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is in the Greek tongue <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, as we be blaſphemed. In the ſame ſenſe it is ſaid 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. being defamed we intreat, the Greek word is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is being blaſphemed we intreat. Again, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.2. we are bid to ſpeak evil of no man falſly, the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118304:19"/>word is, to Blaſpheme no man, revile no man, ſlander no man. Now you, <hi>O Prieſts</hi> are full of ſlandering re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling names; and ſo full of names of Blaſphemy. You Blaſpheme Chriſt and his holy Spirit at every motion or ſtep whereby he moves forward in his people. Every motion that leads forward from under the great myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of iniquity towards <hi>Zion</hi> that you proſecute and dog with revilings, which is nothing elſe but abſolute Blaſphemy. You Blaſpheme both God that leads forth calling him deluſion and Devill, and fancie: and alſo his Tabernacle (that is, his people in motion out of Egypt ſpirituall) calling them Hereticks, Schiſmaticks, Separatiſts, Blaſphemers, and ſuch like, when as in Truth you your ſelves are the things you ſo call. O fools and blind, when will you ſee that the Tabernacle of God dwels under the cloud while its in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: and is to come forth of great tribulation: thats the Character of the Saints under which they muſt ſtand one day. But you by your Blaſphemies, by your ſlanders, and revilings, by odious termes, and other means are great cauſers and promoters of that tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>To the reſt of your Blaſphemies, I think I may not unfitly adde this as one, that you call a building made of wood and ſtone, the Church: whereas the Church is the body of Chriſt. Surely, ſurely the very boyes and children will ere long deride your folly. Your are ſo wedded to this name, that if any call it by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name you deride them, though there be no reaſon why it ſhould be called Church. What! is it the Body of Chriſt? Why will you continue to Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the name of Chriſt thus to call a dead houſe his Body? for the Church is his Body. <hi>Col.</hi> 1, 18, 24. See
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118304:20"/>if you can any where finde a houſe of wood and ſtone called Church in Scripture. If we call it Synagogue, or high place, or Idols Temple, or Cage of every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean and hatefull Bird, we can better juſtifie theſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we finde theſe names given to ſuch like places in Scripture: but theſe you abominate. Or if we call it ſteeple-houſe, or Pulpit-houſe from the form, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct, yet theſe you cannot bear. I would you would tell us what to call them inoffencively. But I muſt tell you that if no name will ſerve you to call them by, but that which is proper to the Body of Chriſt, we muſt in indignation trample them under feet with the names which the Scripture hath given to ſuch houſes, calling them Idols Temples, high places, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>Some I know will frivolouſly anſwer and ſay, Its not the place, but the congregation which we call Church. I ſay thats an idle conceit: for if that were ſo then the name Church ſhould go along with the Congregation. But that it doth not: let the Congregation move all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether if they will to any place, yet the name Church moves not with it, but reſts upon that Idolized Temple, and when none is in it, yet its called Church. Again if you ſhould call the Congregation the Church, yet conſider what you do: for as I ſaid, the Church is the very Body of Chriſt, acted by that Unction which is Chriſt, even by the ſame ſpirit wherewith the perſon of the man Chriſt Jeſus was acted. Take heed how you call a company of people living in Humane inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and traditions, ſatisfying themſelves with the bare name of Chriſtians, having their ſpirits in the earth: I ſay take heed how you call theſe the Body of Chriſt. A company of people acted by a ſpirit of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, vain glory, covetouſneſs, worldly minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118304:20"/>and ſuch like, are theſe the Body of Chriſt acted by his ſpirit, whenas they walk moſt contrary to it? No no, its ſomewhat elſe to be a Chriſtian. It may be ſome will ſay, true, too many do walk ſo, but all do not ſo, ſome walk otherwiſe, and they are the Church. I anſwer, I do not deny but that ſome there, may be of the Church, and not of that earthly Congregation, though among them: but theſe cannot give the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of Church to the reſt, becauſe they are not of them, but onely among them as captive children in Babylon. So that I ſay now, if it were the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation it ſelf (and not the ſtone houſe) which you call Church, yet conſider whether this would be free from Blaſphemie, if they ſhall be found the Synagogue of Satan.</p>
            <p>Theſe now are ſome of thoſe things which may be ſaid concerning you and your Ordinances: both which you wil needs father on Chriſt, crying them up for his Ordinances and your ſelves for his Miniſters: and more then this will the Lord in time diſcover both concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you and others.</p>
            <p>You have ſet up your ſelves as leaders and guides of the people; but you have hardened their hearts againſt the fear of the Lord: and ſo keep them from entering into the very beginnings of wiſdom: for the fear of the <hi>Lord</hi> is the entrance into wiſdom: how ſhould it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that they ſhould be moved to fear him, when as you their teachers, ſay and do not. Do not you thereby teach them to live in ſayings without doings, and that without fear? For by your examples you harden them in an hypocryticall form of words, without doing the will of the Lord: for how do you think that they ſhould learn to do the will of the Lord from your
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118304:21"/>mouthes who are not moved through his fear to do it your ſelves? You ſtand in the way letting and hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men from entring into the Kingdom: and neither enter in your ſelves, nor ſuffer thoſe that are entering to go in; ſo far as you can hinder. If they had not you to reſt upon, they would be ſtirred up the ſooner to look after truth. The people themſelves can ſay of you, that ſome of you ſay well, but you do not as you ſay. This they ſee in the beſt of you: but becauſe of your examples ſet before them they reſt in doing as you do, ſheltering themſelves under your practiſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, although they ſee further. Thus by harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the people in their evil wayes you rob and ſpoil them of that Peace and reſt and light and comfort which obedience to the Truth would lead them into. And ſo for all your boaſting of your miniſtery and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, yet you do not thereby lead up any of the People to thoſe high and noble ends, for which gifts, and miniſtery and the Ordinances of Chriſt were given: namely, to a conformity to Jeſus Chriſt in this world: and to that end were they given, even to lead up to the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8, 11, 12, 13. But how ſhould you lead up further then you goe your ſelves? Nay, your miniſtery is ſo far from leading up to that conformity that the nearer any comes to it, the more are your mouthes opened againſt them in your Pulpits. So that you are of that ſpirit, that ſets it ſelf in the Temple of God over mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences oppoſing and exalting it ſelf above all thats called God; calling that deluſion and fancie. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4.</p>
            <p>Thus I have hitherto finiſhed my Teſtimony againſt that myſtery which is upheld by you, which the Lord is untwiſting. In witneſs againſt which I have been
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118304:21"/>kept back from among you, and have ſuffered the loſſe of all things and do ſuffer: and not onely I but many others. This myſtery of Humane inventions mixed with ſome appearances of Truth hath driven many into the Iland of <hi>Patmos,</hi> (of ſuffering) for many years, even all thoſe <hi>Johns</hi> who have been faithfull to the Revelation of it communicated to them. I for my own part thorow weakneſs and hardneſs of heart, mine own and others have been made for ſometime to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ in <hi>Zoar.</hi> But now beholding ſo great burnings ariſing upon Sodom, I am made to depart out of <hi>Zoar</hi> alſo. Behold there hath been a great Deluge upon the face of the Earth, overtopping all things: but ſome have been preſerved as in an ark: and now I ſee inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Doves ſent forth again (for ſome have returned) to ſee if the waters be abated from the tops of the mountains: if that ſpirit of innocency finde nothing but an Olive leaf, it muſt return again untill the waters be further abated: theſe I write for thoſe who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>And now I ſhall leave one Querie with you who are the Nationall Miniſters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray tell me who are thoſe Sorcerers which have been ſo numerous that they have bewitched and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived all Nations? thoſe Enchanters who have made the inhabiters of the earth drunke with the wine of their fornication? and with whom the Kings of the earth have been ſo good friends that they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted fornication with them?</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:118304:22"/>
            <head>Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THeſe things which I have written are not from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to draw people off from theſe men to follow or hing upon my ſelf: no, but to witneſs with the reſt of my fellow ſufferers againſt Deluſion: and to help to bring down that proud Lording ſpirit which is in the new Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates; which would ſit as God in the Temple of God, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it over mens conſciences through fained words, and cauſing poor ſlaves and ſouls of men to dread them even as God himſelf. I ſay my deſire is to be helpfull to bring down to the duſt that deluding Lording ſpirit, That the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of people may ſtand open and free to the voice of the Lord in them: and may not be captivated with ſuch who live in words. And if after theſe, others ſhall ariſe into the ſame ſpirit, as theſe have riſen into the ſpirit of the Prelates after their deceaſe, He that hath diſcovered them, and theſe, will alſo diſcover ſuch as ſhall ſucceed; and ſo in this ſenſe, as well as in outward Governments, Overturn, Overturn, Overturn, untill he come into his Temple whoſe right it is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You may call theſe things which I have written flaſhes of new light if you pleaſe (for ſo you brand every thing that breaks forth now in this dawning of the morning after the ſad night of Antichriſtian darkneſs.) But be it known to you it is not ſo to me, being that ſame which hath been ſprinking up in me and others theſe many years. For you have been a long time repreſented to me as men under thick darkneſs, which hath kept me off thorow the tender mercy of my God from entering into your wayes in which I could ſee no light. I have been onely brought to the brink of your Babyloniſh Rivers, which bring up your
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118304:22"/>gain, I mean your Ordinances, that I might taſte of the bitterneſs of them; but there have I been made to ſit down weeping in remembrance of</hi> Zion: <hi>which</hi> Zion <hi>haſtens to appear.</hi> Allelujah.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou that readeſt theſe things and art convinced of the truth of them, Boaſt not againſt theſe men: But look towards the Lord who is making his righteous Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments manifeſt; and fear. For he will in due time diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover much more then this, both concerning them and others. He is about to</hi> fan the Nations, <hi>and to gather his wheat into his Garner, and to burn up the light chaff with unquenchable fire therefore Glory not. But let him that thinketh heſtandeth take heed leſt he fall. Be not high mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but fear. For my part I write not theſe things out of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs againſt any of their perſons, or to boaſt over any of them, (for the Lord can ſoon make a blaſpheming Saul to become a Paul.) But rather to let proud boaſting, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling Preachers to ſee, what little cauſe they have to carry ſo clamorouſly againſt thoſe who withdraw from them. In reſpect of my ſelf I had rather be ſilent, and let them plow all the day long upon my back with their revil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. But if theſe things ſhall be inſtrumentall to bring ſome of them to conſider their wayes, and to look better to the foundation of their practiſes, and to ceaſe from beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their fellow-ſervants and be ſtirred up to ſeek the way to</hi> Zion <hi>thats as much as I look for: Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:118304:23"/>
            <head>A Letter to the Papiſts.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving touched in diſcourſe with you upon that which is the very foundation of your Religion, and ſeeing it in my underſtanding to have nothing but the ſands to ſtand upon, I cannot but in love to you, repreſent again before you the ſame thing that I then ſaid to you, that you may ſeriouſly ponder it for it overturns your Religion at the very root. Your foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is this, that <hi>Peter</hi> muſt have a ſucceſſion, and ſecondly that the Biſhops of Rome are the onely ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of <hi>Peter:</hi> and ſo they being the ſucceſſors of <hi>Peter</hi> are the Church built upon him the Rock, and from them all Teaching muſt flow. Here is your Baſis or foundation on which you ſtand.</p>
            <p>Now friends conſider whether an outward ſucceſſion of Bodies inhabiting the place where <hi>Peter</hi> lived (if he lived at Rome) be a good foundation for the Church of Chriſt to ſtand upon. When Chriſt the promiſed ſeed came, you know that the Church ſlipt away from the carnall ſeed to a ſpirituall, leaving the carnall Jew boaſting of its carnall ſucceſſion, when as yet God had departed from it. Now ſhall we think that God would ever after tie himſelf to a carnall ſucceſſion again, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once cut off <hi>Abrahams</hi> who was the friend of God? Certainly if any may ſtand upon an outward ſucceſſion, then <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed after the fleſh may, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo many Promiſes running to them in outward appearance. But he is not a Jew now who is one out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, neither is Circumciſion that which is outward in the fleſh: but he is a Jew who is one inwardly: and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118304:23"/>Circumciſion is that of the heart, and they who are of the faith of <hi>Abraham</hi> are counted for the ſeed. So I ſay, he is not of the ſucceſſion of <hi>Peter</hi> who is one out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, but he who is of the ſame ſpirit with <hi>Peter.</hi> No Nation or place, or outward order of men can confine the ſucceſſion of <hi>Peter</hi> to themſelves, ſince God laid aſide all ſuch outward entailment from <hi>Abraham,</hi> and hath betaken himſelf onely to a ſpirituall line, a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſeed. For it were contrary to all reaſon that God ſhould lay aſide or cut off <hi>Abrahams</hi> carnall ſeed of the Jewes, to take in a ſpirituall ſeed out of any Nation, and yet after that take up again a carnall or outward ſucceſſion to <hi>Peter,</hi> and that in one part of one Nation only, namely at Rome. For this were to build up again that which he had formerly deſtroyed; and to deſtroy that which formerly he had built up. To build up again a carnal ſucceſſion to <hi>Peter,</hi> which he had deſtroyed in <hi>Abrahams</hi> line; and to deſtroy and keep out a ſpirituall ſeed fearing God in all Nations which once he had taken in. The Progreſſe of the Lord with his Church is not a going back from ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to Carnall, but a going forward from carnall to ſpirituall, and after that to more ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>Now that the Biſhops of Rome are not the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſeed nor the ſpirituall ſucceſſors of <hi>Peter,</hi> nor the Rock upon which the Church of Chriſt is builded, no nor the Church of Chriſt it ſelf; nor the ſole feeders of the flock of Chriſt, no nor fit to be feeders of the flock of Chriſt at all, appears clearly by their lives. You ſhall know them by their fruits or works, ſaith Chriſt, (ſpeaking of falſe Prophets:) do men gather grapes of thorns or figgs of thiſtles? No they are ſo far from being diſcovered by their fruits to be <hi>Peters</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:118304:24"/>ſpirituall ſucceſſors, that their fruits diſcover them to be falſe Prophets, yea and ſuch as have the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence among thoſe who have deceived the Nations. This ſtands in great Characters upon their foreheads that all may run and read, <hi>Mistery Babylon the great, the mother of Harlots, and abominations of the Earth:</hi> For what abominations be there, that are not among them committed? As for perſecution they excell, being drunk with the blood of Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5, 6. They are arayed in purple, and ſcarlet colour, and decked with gold, and pretious ſtone, and pearls, having a golden cup in their hand full of abominations, and filthineſs of their fornication. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. How far are theſe things differing from the ſpirit that was in <hi>Peter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to ſpeak a little more particularly, that they are not <hi>Peters</hi> ſpirituall ſucceſſors appears in this becauſe they are the leaſt conformable or like to <hi>Peter</hi> of any men. For <hi>Peter</hi> did really in life deny himſelf, take up his croſſe and follow Chriſt: they do not ſo, but are exalted like Princes in the earth, poſſeſſing an earthly Kingdom. They have indeed many images of croſſes, they glory in the ſhadow but deny the practiſe, the life of the croſſe, which is that which Chriſt called for, and <hi>Peter</hi> lived in, but they are far from. Again as they have not the life of Peter, ſo they have not the ſpirit of Peter in them, and therefore are not his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and ſo are not a Rock for the Church of Chriſt to be built upon. It was not Peters outſide that was called a Rock, but that ſpirit of life that was in him, which could flow into the ſpirits of others and ſo ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment many living ſtones into one ſpirituall houſe with him. Now that they have not the ſpirit of Peter in them
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:118304:24"/>appears alſo by their fruits, their lives: their fruits are the fruits of Sodom, and not the fruits of the ſpirit: for they live in pride, fulneſs of bread, abundance of idleneſs, covetouſneſs, Perſecution and ſuch like. They ſeek the honor of this world, and heap up to themſelves, the riches of this world, and therefore cannot be Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, much leſs Rocks for the Church to ſtand on, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.44. How can ye beleeve who receive honor one of another, and ſeek not the honor that cometh from God onely? Now none receive greater honor among men then they do: therefore none are further off from beleeving in Chriſt aright then they are. Again they have not the true love of God in them. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.15. If any man love the world the love of the Father is not in him. And who are greater lovers of the world then the Biſhops of Rome are? Again they are not fit to teach others. This alſo appears by their lives. For what have they to do to take the word of God into their mouthes, who hate to be reformed themſelves, and to live as Chriſt and his Apoſtles did? How can they build up the Church of Chriſt by their Doctrine, who live contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt? How can they teach men to take up the croſſe and follow Chriſt, who are enemies to the croſſe of Chriſt? whoſe God is their Belly, who glory in that which will be their ſhame, who minde earthly things? <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18, 19.</p>
            <p>Thus I ſay their lives diſcover them to be nothing conformable to Peter; to have none of that ſpirit in them, which dwelt in him; to be unbeleevers; to want the love of the Father in them; to be unfit to teach others. All theſe I ſay appear clearly by their lives, by their fruits, by their works; the Character that Chriſts gives to know falſe Prophets day. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118304:25"/>16.20. And ſhall any man then look upon theſe men, as Peters, as Rocks on which the Church ſtands, as feeders of the ſheep of the Lambs of Chriſt; as the head of the Church: and patterns for the Church of Chriſt to follow? Friends it is love to you and the Truth which makes me to repreſent theſe things to you. And I deſire that you may well conſider where you ſtand, and on what you hang: whether you ſtand on the Rock Chriſt, or on the ſands of an outward ſucceſſion: whether you hang on a ſure naile, or on a weak ſlippery pin. It behoves all to conſider well their foundation, for the Lord is comming to diſcover the foundations of the Earth, and to ſhake them till all the buildings raiſed up upon the ſands do fall, though never ſo glorious.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. Tomlinſon.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118304:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
